I’ve always known I was meant to go away.
I grew up looking at the travellers. Every year in spring they were going, hundreds of them, taking over the sky.
I remember asking my mom: “Can I go too?”
“Your time will come, Mawusi”, she said. “Soon enough my darling. Now eat, so you’ll be stronger.”
I remember looking at them. So free. So proud. So strong.
So I ate. I did grow stronger. But I couldn’t grow fast enough for my ambition.
“Why do you want to go?” Other birds asked. “Can’t you see this is the best place on earth?
Nowhere else will you find a forest so lush, a sky so blue, a water so pure...
Their sky is grey, over there, their air is cold, their water is full of oil. Don’t you know? Or maybe you just think you are better than us?”
I looked at them. They were parrots, birds of paradise, lovebirds.
They were so big, so beautiful, the kings of this place. They belonged.
They couldn’t understand us. They couldn’t understand that for us, leaving was surviving.
There was a lone traveller living close to our nest. His name was Nunyati.
He had done the journey many times, but now he was too old.
I loved listening to his stories. I kept finding excuses to get close to him. He used to chase the other birds away, but I think he liked me.
“You are so young, Mawusi. I used to be like you, I wouldn’t listen to anyone, I just wanted to go.
But if only you knew the risks. Oh sweet child, you don’t know what’s out there.
You don’t know the cold, the fear in your bones. If birds knew what awaited them, they would never leave.”
“If you had known, would you have gone anyway?”
He took a long pause, looked at the sky. He laughed.
“Probably. We travellers are a mad species. It’s in our blood, we can’t fight it.
Just listen to your mother, Mawusi. Eat. Grow stronger. You’ll need all the strength you can get.
Your time has almost come.”